Hello, and welcome to this lesson
on signing images and enabling Docker Content Trust.
Docker Content Trust is essentially a feature of Docker
that provides us a way to sign our container images.
From a security standpoint, if you're going to be running
any kind of software in your systems,
it's important to be able to verify
that that software hasn't been tampered with by an attacker.
So in the non-container world,
you'll often find various mechanisms for signing software
basically providing some kind of signature or certificate
to certify the integrity of that software
and the same holds true when it comes to Docker containers.
So with Docker Content Trust, essentially what happens
is the image creator generates a certificate or signature,
which can then be used to validate
that the image has not been tampered with
before running it on our system.
Typically this certificate and signature data
is stored right alongside the image in a Docker registry.
So we can sign the image, we can push the image
and the signature data to the registry
and then when we or anyone else
goes to pull or run that image,
that signature data can be used
to verify the integrity of the image before running it.
So the first thing I want to do
is to show you how to sign an image
and push it to a registry,
and for this lesson,
we're just going to use Docker Hub for our registry.
So I'm going to go ahead and do a docker login
to log in to Docker Hub.
Now that I'm logged into Docker Hub,
I need to create what's called a trust key
or a delegation key pair,
and this is basically a key that identifies me as a user.
I'm just going to make sure that I'm in my home directory
with the cd ~/
and then I can generate my trust key
just with this command docker trust key generate
and then I will enter my Docker Hub username.
So if you're following along,
you will need an account on Docker Hub,
you can find a link to Docker Hub down below the video
if you need to create an account,
but if you're following along,
you'll need to enter your Docker Hub username here.
Mine is willbla, I'm going to go ahead and run that
and I need to enter a passphrase,
and then I need to reenter that passphrase.
Now make sure that you make a note of that passphrase
because you will need it later.
So now I've generated my trust key.
So the next thing I'm going to do
is I'm going to add myself as a signer
to a new repository in Docker Hub.
So I can do that with the docker trust signer add command
and I need to pass in my --key
and there's a file here in my home directory.
This file was actually generated
by that last command that we ran and it's willbla.pub.
That's my public key, so I'm going to go ahead
and specify that as the key file,
then I need to enter my Docker Hub username,
so that's just going to be willbla.
Again, you're going to need
to enter your Docker Hub username there,
and then I'll enter the repository name.
So I'll just make this a personal repository.
So I will prefix that with my Docker Hub username here
followed by a forward slash, and I'll just call it dct-test
because we're just testing Docker Content Trust.
So when I run that, it's going to ask me for a passphrase
for the root key here.
So I'll need to create this new passphrase and repeat it
and then I'll need to create a passphrase
for the repository key as well.
Now that I've created my passphrases,
I have successfully added myself as a signer
to this repository.
So now that I've added myself as a signer,
let's go ahead and just create an image
that we can use for testing.
I'll just make a directory here called dct-test
and then I'll change directory into that new directory
and I'll create a Dockerfile.
So we'll just create a very simple image here.
I'll just do FROM busybox:latest
and for my CMD, I'll just print a message to the screen.
So we'll just print the message, It worked!
So a very simple image,
we're just going to use this for testing.
So now let's go ahead and build our image here
and I'm going to give it a tag and it will be that
repository that I added myself to as a signer, my Docker Hub
username, of course you'll need to use your Docker Hub
username, /dct-test and I'll give it a tag here, :unsigned.
Nothing special about that tag name,
just a descriptive tag name.
We're going to create an unsigned version of this image.
So I'm just going to call it unsigned
just so we know what it is.
Then space and a dot to build from the current directory.
So we're going to push this image
to Docker Hub without signing it,
so it's just going to be a regular unsigned image
in Docker Hub.
We'll just do a docker push.
So now we have an unsigned version of that image.
The reason I'm creating an unsigned image here
is because I want to show you how Docker Content Trust
behaves with both signed and unsigned images.
So we're going to start with just a normal unsigned image
here. So now that I've built my image,
let's just go ahead and run it
just to make sure that it works,
and we can see my output here, it just says, It worked!,
which is our output that we put in our command
in the Dockerfile.
So it looks like my image runs just fine.
So this is an unsigned image.
So let's see what happens
when we enable DOCKER_CONTENT_TRUST.
So I'm going to show you how to do that now,
and all I need to do is set this environment variable
called DOCKER_CONTENT_TRUST.
If I set that variable equal to 1,
Docker Content Trust is now enabled.
So let's see what happens if I do this docker run again.
This time it says, No valid trust data for my unsigned tag.
Essentially, what it's saying is, this image is unsigned.
There's no signature data available,
therefore it's not going to run that image
because DOCKER_CONTENT_TRUST is enabled.
So now I'm going to go ahead
and show you how we can sign our images.
So I'm just going to do another docker build -t,
my Docker Hub username, /dct-test
and we'll create a tag called :signed.
Again, just a descriptive name there,
just so we know that this is a signed version of our image.
I'm just going to rebuild that image with a different tag
and I can sign it with
docker trust sign willbla/dct-test:signed.
Now be aware, the docker trust sign command
also pushes the image to the registry.
So this command is going to generate a signature
and it will push the signature data
as well as the image itself to Docker Hub.
So it's basically like docker push,
but it also signs the image.
Now, when I'm signing my image
I do need to enter my passphrase.
This is the first passphrase that we created in this lesson
when we used that docker trust key generate command.
So enter that passphrase
and our image was successfully signed and pushed.
Now, let's see what happens when we try to run that image.
I'll run willbla/dct-test and the signed tag,
and sure enough, we see our output.
We were able to successfully run that image
because it is properly signed.
Another interesting thing to note is
when you have Docker Content Trust enabled
with that DOCKER_CONTENT_TRUST environment variable,
when you do a regular docker push,
it will automatically sign the image.
So when DOCKER_CONTENT_TRUST is set to 1,
docker push pretty much behaves
exactly like docker trust sign.
So with Docker Content Trust enabled,
we were unable to run the unsigned image
but we were able to run the signed image.
Now let's disable DOCKER_CONTENT_TRUST,
and that's easy to do.
We just need to set that environment variable back to 0.
Now that it's disabled,
I can do a docker run willbla/dct-test on my unsigned image.
So with Docker Content Trust disabled,
we can run both signed and unsigned images on our host.
So we talked a little bit about what Docker Content Trust is
and what it does.
I showed you how to sign your Docker images
and then I demonstrated how to enable and disable
Docker Content Trust on your system
and we experimented a little bit with
what happens when we try to run signed and unsigned images
with Docker Content Trust enabled and disabled.
That's all for this lesson. See you in the next one.