Hello, and welcome to this lesson
on default Docker engine security. We're going to be talking
about some of the basic security features that come packaged
with Docker.
These are just a few concepts that you need to
be generally familiar with
for the Docker Certified Associate exam.
So I want to start by talking
about namespaces and control groups.
Now we've already talked about namespaces
and control groups previously in this course,
but I want to talk about what these 2 concepts have
to do specifically with security.
Namespaces and control groups primarily influence security
by providing isolation to containers.
Isolation means that container processes cannot
see or affect other containers or processes that
are running directly on the host.
So container isolation basically just means
that what's going on inside the container can't
affect things that are going on outside the container.
So how does this isolation that is provided
through namespaces and control groups, influence security?
Well, isolation limits the impact
of exploits and privilege escalation attacks.
So if an attacker is able to influence your container
or gain control of your container through some kind
of exploit or vulnerability in the container,
isolation limits their ability to utilize that control
to gain control of other containers
or potentially to gain control of the host itself.
So with that isolation, if a container is compromised,
it's much more difficult for an attacker
to utilize that level of control
that they've gained inside the container to
gain any further control outside the container.
Another thing you need to be aware
of when it comes to security with regard
to the Docker engine is the Docker daemon attack surface.
The Docker daemon itself that is running
on your host presents an attack surface
that could be vulnerable if you leave it exposed.
So it's important to understand how the Docker daemon works
and ensure that you don't give anything or anyone access
to it that shouldn't have that access because
the Docker daemon itself does require root privileges.
Essentially, what that means is
if someone is able to gain control of your Docker daemon
or they're able to execute things using your Docker daemon,
they may be able to use that control
in order to escalate their privileges
and gain further control of your systems.
So that is something that
in the security world we refer to as an attack surface.
It's something that a malicious person may desire to attack
in order to accomplish whatever their malicious goals are.
So with that in mind, it is very important
to only allow trusted users access to the Docker daemon.
We talked earlier about how to give individual users access
to run Docker commands,
and you want to make sure that you don't give that access
to anyone that shouldn't have it.
That includes both human users and automated processes.
So for example, if you're building some automation
that's able to interact with the Docker daemon,
just be aware that there needs to be some scrutiny
around that with regard to security,
because you don't want an attacker to be able to
gain control of the daemon through whatever users
or processes are given access to that.
The final thing I want to talk
about in this lesson is Linux kernel capabilities.
Capabilities are a concept within the Linux kernel,
and essentially what capabilities do is they
allow you to give fine-grained control
to entities within the Linux environment.
Docker utilizes these capabilities
to fine tune what containers and processes can access.
So namespaces and control groups have a lot
of influence over what those container processes can access
and capabilities can be used to grant specific abilities
to containers without granting unnecessary
additional abilities.
Capabilities are not generally something
that you need to be aware of
when you're actually using Docker,
but for the purposes of the exam, you need to be aware
that Docker uses capabilities internally
in order to securely provide some
of its functionality.
Specifically, it uses capabilities
to grant fine-grained abilities
to container processes without the need
for those processes to run as root.
So I'll give you an example. In a typical Linux environment,
you have just to run as root in order to listen
on a port below 1024,
but we have run containers throughout this course
that for example, nginx containers, that listen on port 80.
Normally you would have to run as root
in order to do that.
But Docker is able to use capabilities to
grant a container process the ability to listen on a port
below 1024 without having to run as root.
So that's just an example
of how Docker uses those fine-grained capabilities to
give some kind of access to a process
without having to allow that process to run as root.
So, as you can imagine
that's pretty important from a security standpoint
because it allows the container process to do what
it needs to do, without granting unnecessary privileges.
So we've talked about a few general concepts
that you may need to be aware of for
the Docker Certified Associate exam.
We talked about the relationship between namespaces
and control groups and how they provide security isolation.
We talked about the Docker daemon attack surface
and how you should be cautious when granting any user
or process access to the Docker daemon,
and we also talked about Linux capabilities
and how Docker uses those to grant fine-grained permission
to container processes without giving them root access.
That's all for this lesson.
See you in the next one.