Hello, and welcome to this lesson
on Docker swarm security and MTLS.
So we're just going to talk about a couple of concepts
related to security in the context of Docker swarm,
and the first concept I want to talk about,
is encrypting overlay networks.
So we've already talked about overlay networks,
these are those distributed cluster networks
that allow your containers and services
to communicate transparently across your swarm cluster,
regardless of which node in the cluster they may be on.
But what if we want to encrypt all communication
going across those overlay networks?
Well, that's what we're going to talk about.
It's actually pretty easy to do.
I'm going to create a Docker overlay network
just like we have done in the past
with the docker network create command,
and I can encrypt my network
just by passing in this --opt encrypted flag,
and I'll specify my --driver to make it an overlay network,
and I'll just give it the name, my-encrypted-net,
and just like that I've created
an encrypted overlay network.
Now, it's not much fun just to create the network,
so let's go ahead and actually demonstrate
using the network just to make sure
that it's really working.
So I'm just going to create a simple service here
and I'll just make a service running nginx,
as we have done many times before,
and I'll make sure that it's using that network,
my-encrypted-net,
we'll give it 3 replicas,
and just make it a simple nginx service.
Now, in order to demonstrate communication
across that encrypted network,
let's go ahead and create another service.
We'll just call this one encrypted-overlay-busybox,
and again, we will attach it to my-encrypted-net
and we will do the radial/busyboxplus:curl image,
just so we can communicate with our nginx service,
and I'll just pass in a simple command here,
sh -c and then in single quotes,
I'll put my command, and just like any other network,
we should be able to contact our nginx service
simply using the service name here,
and I'll just use port 80,
and just so that busybox container
doesn't shut down immediately, I'll have it sleep.
So, now our busybox service is running
and we should be able to check the log
for our busybox service,
and in that log, we should see the nginx welcome page
as a response to this curl command here
demonstrating communication over our encrypted network.
So I'll just do docker service logs
on my encrypted-overlay-busybox service there,
and sure enough, it's a little bit
squashed here on the screen,
but we can see the output from our nginx welcome page.
So we created an encrypted network
and we were able to successfully communicate
between 2 different services
using that encrypted overlay network.
The other thing I want to talk to you about,
is MTLS, or mutual TLS, in Docker swarm.
MTLS refers to mutually authenticated
transport layer security.
So this is basically normal TLS,
but it means that both the client
and the server have a certificate.
That's what we're talking about
when we talk about mutually authenticated TLS.
The client knows that the server really is the server
and the server knows that the client really is the client.
They have both authenticated with each other
and all communication between the 2 is encrypted.
So when we talk about MTLS in the context of Docker swarm,
what we're talking about is the communication
between the different nodes and components in the cluster.
So when our worker nodes are talking to our manager nodes,
or the manager nodes are talking to the worker nodes,
or when the manager nodes are talking to each other,
all of that swarm level communication
is encrypted and mutually authenticated.
So for the purposes of the Docker Certified Associate,
you need to just have a general awareness of the concept
behind this mutually authenticated transport layer security
for those swarm level communications.
You don't need to memorize every single detail
about how this works,
but I'll just give you a general idea of what it looks like.
So when we're talking about MTLS,
both of the participants in the communication.
So let's say our swarm manager
is talking to one of our worker nodes,
both of those participants would exchange certificates
and all their communication
would be authenticated and encrypted.
So the way this works is when we initialize a new swarm,
so when we do that docker swarm init command
and create our first manager node,
a root certificate or certificate authority is generated,
and this certificate authority
is then used to generate and sign
all of the future certificates
for all the new nodes as they joined the cluster.
Now worker and manager tokens
are also generated using the CA,
so you may remember when we joined our node,
we used a command that came from the manager
and contained a special token.
Well, that token was generated using the CA.
So when we add the worker node,
it has that validated token
that came from the certificate authority,
and when the node joins the cluster
it gets its own certificate,
which is used to authenticate
and encrypt those communications
between the manager and the worker.
So our MTLS is used for all cluster level communication
between the swarm nodes.
So, if we are spinning up new services
and the manager needs to assign a new task to a worker,
it's going to communicate with the worker node
to tell the worker node to spin up a new container,
and that communication is going to occur
in that mutually authenticated encrypted and secure fashion.
MTLS is enabled by default,
you don't need to do anything to enable it or configure it.
It's already turned on and we've been using it
all along through this course
while we've been using Docker swarm.
But you do need to just be generally aware
of the fact that all of these cluster level communications
are encrypted with mutually authenticated encryption.
So we've talked about 2 basic concepts
related to security in Docker swarm.
We talked about encrypting overlay networks,
and we talked about the mutually authenticated encryption
that is used to handle all cluster level communication
in Docker swarm.
That's all for this lesson. See you in the next one.