Hello, and welcome to this lesson
on securing the Docker daemon HTTP socket.
So Docker by default listens on a socket
that is not exposed to the network.
and that means there's no way
for anyone to interact with your Docker daemon
from outside your server, via the network,
and as you can imagine, that's pretty good for security.
However, you do have the ability
to expose that Docker socket externally
so that you can interact with your Docker daemon
from outside the server and manage it remotely.
There is a way to do this securely
but it does require some additional configuration.
Specifically, we will need to create a certificate authority
and set up client and server certificates that we can use
in order to securely connect to the Docker socket.
So I went ahead and created 2 playground servers
specifically for this lesson.
You can just use 2 servers
with Ubuntu 18.04 Bionic Beaver LTS, and a size of micro.
We really don't need to do a whole lot on these servers
so we can keep them pretty small,
and that way, you have enough units left over
that if you have a Docker swarm
and you want to hang onto your Docker swarm
and not interfere with it, you can just keep that around
and just use those 2 remaining units
for these 2 microservers.
I went ahead and installed Docker Community Edition
on both of my servers as well,
however, I did not add a cloud_user to the Docker group.
So if I just do a docker version here,
you'll notice I got permission denied,
indicating that I cannot actually connect
to the Docker daemon,
and I just wanted to do that just so it will be clear
once we've gotten everything up and running and working,
we'll know that we're actually connecting
to that remote daemon
and not just connecting to the local one.
We can easily test it
just by running that docker version command.
Now this server that I'm looking at right now,
I'm going to use as my server side.
So here's where I'm going to go ahead
and generate all of my certificates.
Now, if you want to follow along,
you can find these commands that I'm going to use
in the description below the video.
Just make sure that if you're copying and pasting,
you replace any placeholders in those commands
with the actual values that need to be there.
So first I'm going to run this command
and this is going to generate a key
for my certificate authority,
and I do need to enter a passphrase
and then I'll reenter that passphrase.
Now make sure you remember the passphrase that you use
because you will need it just a little later.
Now that I have my ca-key file,
I'm going to go ahead and generate the CA certificate
and of course right there, I need that passphrase again.
Next I'm going to generate a key file for my server key.
Now, in order to generate the actual server certificate,
I do need to provide some additional information
in form of a certificate signing request.
So I'm going to go ahead and run this command
which is just going to create that server.csr.
That's just a temporary file that we need
in order to generate our certificate.
Next, I'm going to create this extfile.cnf,
it's just a configuration file
for the certificate that I'm going to generate
and there is a placeholder here that I need to remove.
It says server private IP.
So I'm going to remove that placeholder
and I will paste in the private IP address
of my cloud server here
that I'm going to be using as my Docker daemon servers.
So I'm just going to run that
and then I do need to add 1 more line
to that extfile.cnf file,
setting extendedKeyUsage to serverAuth.
Now that I've created all those files,
I'm ready to go ahead and generate my server certificate
and I need to enter that passphrase.
If I do an ls at this point,
you can see that I have several files.
I have my ca.pem and my ca-key,
those are the 2 files for my certificate authority
and of course, server-cert.pem and server-key,
the 2 files for my server certificate.
Now we also need to generate a client certificate
that our Docker client is going to use
in order to authenticate with the Docker daemon.
So I'm just going to create another key.
This one is going to be for the client
and I need to create
another certificate signing request file.
This one will just be called client.csr
and another config file.
and this time we're just outputting this one line
to extfile-client.cnf and last but not least,
I can go ahead and generate the client certificate itself
and I do need to enter my passphrase.
Now that I've done that,
you can see that I have my cert.pem and my key.pem.
Those are the 2 files for my client certificate.
The next thing I'm going to do,
is I'm going to go ahead and set some appropriate
permissions for these files because some of them are
sensitive, particularly those key files.
So I'm just going to do a couple of chmod commands
to change the permissions of those files appropriately,
and now I'm ready to go ahead
and configure my Docker host to utilize these client files
and to expose that socket externally
so that I can access it remotely.
So I'm just going to clear the screen
and do a sudo vi on etc/docker/daemon.json.
So we're just going to change that Docker daemon file
and because this is a fresh server with a Docker
installation, I don't have anything in my daemon.json at the
moment, so I'm just going to paste in this content here.
We're setting tlsverify to true
and then we're passing in 3 of those files
that we just created:
our certificate authority, as well as the server
certificate, and the server certificate key.
So I'm going to go ahead and save that file.
Now I'm not quite finished configuring the Docker daemon,
I also need to edit my Docker daemon unit file
which is in /lib/systemd/system/docker.service.
So I'm going to make a change to that file,
and I'm looking for the line that begins with ExecStart,
it's right here under the service block.
and here's the line that says ExecStart
and there's this flag here, -H.
I need to change the value of that flag.
Right now it's fd://, I'm just going to remove that
and I'm going to change it to 0.0.0.0:2376
and I'll go ahead and save that file.
Now because we made a change to the unit file,
we do need to do a systemctl daemon-reload
and now we're ready to go ahead and restart Docker.
Now that I've done that,
I need to go ahead and copy some of these files
that I generated to my client.
I'm going to need that client certificate
as well as my certificate authority.
So I'm going to scp ca.pem and cert.pem
as well as key.pem, my client key,
and I will just copy those to cloud_user@
and then I'm going to paste in
the private IP of my playground server
that I'm going to be using as the client here
and then I'll put a colon
and specify a destination directory of /home/cloud_user,
and I'll accept that key
and of course I need to enter my normal cloud_user password.
So now I have copied those 3 files to the client server.
So I'm going to move over here to the client
and if I do an ls, I should see those 3 files
that I just copied over from the server.
So now I need to move those files into a specific location
and it's just going to be in my home directory /.docker.
So I need to go ahead and create that directory
because it doesn't exist right now.
So I went ahead and created that directory
and then I will copy those files
and I can do that all with 1 command, just like this,
in curly braces, I'll just put
and all 3 files end in .pem,
and I'll just copy those 3 into that Docker directory,
and if I list the contents of that directory,
I can see my 3 files there,
and now I just need to configure my local Docker client
to connect to the daemon on my Docker server.
So to do that, I can just set some environment variables,
and the first one I need to set is DOCKER_HOST
and I need to set that to tcp://
and then, I need to enter the private IP address
of my Docker server.
That's the first server that we were working on earlier.
So I'm just going to go ahead and paste that in
and then I need to set the port, so :2376
and I'm also going to set a second environment variable
called DOCKER_TLS_VERIFY and I'll just set that to 1
to put that in TLS verify mode,
and let's go ahead and just run this docker version command
and sure enough, we got a response from the server.
Again, I did not add my cloud_user to the docker group,
so that response is not coming from the local Docker daemon,
it is coming from the remote Docker daemon.
We are connecting to the daemon on the other server
and we can interact with Docker
just using any of our normal Docker commands.
If I do docker ps,
this response is coming from that other server.
If I run a container,
that container is going to run on that other server,
and all of that communication is encrypted and secured
using client and server certificates.
So in this lesson, we talked about
how to securely authenticate against a remote Docker daemon
using the HTTP socket.
I showed you how to generate
the client and server certificates
and configure the server to use them.
and I also showed you how to configure the Docker client
to connect to that remote socket on another server.
That's all for this lesson.
See you in the next one.